[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software work OS is a modern identity
platform built for B2B SAS it provides
easy to ous apis for authentication user
identity and complex Enterprise features
like SSO and skim provisioning workos is
a drop-in replacement for ozero and
supports up to 1 million monthly active
users for free it's perfect for B2B SAS
companies frustrated with high costs
opaque pricing and lack of Enterprise
capabilities supported by Legacy off
vendors today hundreds of high growth
scale UPS use work OS including ones you
probably know like versel web flow and
Loom check out work
os.com to learn
more
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Jeff dittle I'm excited to
invite John fransen as a guest on the
show today for a conversation about
geospatial Technologies John fransen is
the chief product officer for elase a
content and data management solution for
digital Maps he worked on SRE
Technologies and Licensing with
early.com companies such as eat ESPN
outdoors and Reserve America this became
the initial footprint for a product he
started in 20 2007 called geoc consensus
accidentally one of the first headless
content Management Systems which helped
power National Geographic maps in 2020
geoc consensus was relaunched as elase
an API first data management platform
for digital Maps John welcome to the
show hey thanks Jeff glad you're here
let's start with sharing a little bit
about how you got into mapping certainly
you know I've always been interested in
maps and even as a kid I had maps on the
wall back before there were such things
as digital maps and I'd look at them in
the evenings and especially was
interested in places that kind of just
seemed out of the way and kind of
distant and remote and always kind of
wondered what it was like at those
places digital Maps did something kind
of interesting and new where it made
suddenly the world accessible especially
with the Advent of satellite imagery and
such and so maybe on one side it took
took away the mystery of the world but
on the other side is it it opened it up
to us and then at a certain point there
was a a project that I was kind of
working on in the late 1990s where there
was this intersection between what we
needed to accomplish and Maps okay tell
us a little bit more about that what was
the project and how did Maps become a
part of what problems you were solving
so we were building something for the
Coleman company maybe some people are
familiar with that that's the guys who
make lanterns and stoves and and outdoor
stuff back at that time Coleman wanted
to expand their brand a bit beyond just
you know kind of selling coolers and
sleeping bags and backpacks and stuff
like that they wanted to help people and
facilitate people to find places to go
and things to do outside and we
discovered that at least in the US for
people who are familiar with the us
there are these really popular places
called national forests and they have
campgrounds in them that are people go
and stay at and the US Forest Service at
that time didn't really even know how
many campgrounds they actually had and
so what we were going to do is build a
database of every National Forest
campground and there were about
4,500 or so of them across the us and we
had about six months to pull that off
and this was pretty early it wasn't like
you could just go online like you can
now to find this information so we had
to build a data set of about you know 45
to 5,000 different places and to do that
we needed to enlist people we'd call
field experts which were kind of like
the forest rangers and such so they
could log in and tell us about these
different campgrounds and then we wanted
also to know where they're at and so we
started to log kind of like the the
coordinates the geoc coordinates for
this the latitude longitude of this and
that tool that allowed people to
interact kind of remotely to fac
facilitate geospatial information we
called it consensus at that time it was
kind of the very first iterations people
thought it was kind of cool back then to
kind of be able to log in and
collaborate on places you know I think
the coolness is worn off nowadays we
kind of take it for granted now I think
yeah we're pretty kind of burned out on
maybe filling in fields online
but and so we did that enlisted you know
literally hundreds if not maybe even
thousands of people to all collaborate
on building this data set and then it
became something we want that Coleman
called the outernet so the internet was
pretty cool back then but then they said
let's go let's make something called the
outernet and it was a online travel
planning site where you could literally
say I want to start here and go there
and it's going to show you the
campgrounds along the way with
descriptions of it and such like that it
might seem pretty pedestrian right now
but this was before Google Maps existed
yeah 25 years ago and I think it's
interesting that that predate social
media and yet here they were telling
people to get outside and it seems like
now we're realizing that's still a good
thing to get off the tech and get
outside but we're here to talk about
tech so in that vein let's dive a little
deeper into the nuts and bolts of
mapping applications some of our
listeners may have experienced building
mapping applications I'm pretty sure all
of them have some experience using
interactive maps but for those who
either have limited experience or no
experience with maps share a little bit
about how interactive mapping
applications work what's the nuts and
bolts behind
yeah certainly one of the things I found
really interesting just to kind of start
with on this is like there was a study
done in
2019 by the National Academy of Sciences
and MIT and it had asked people what do
you find most valuable about the
internet and the first you know at the
top of the list was search and you know
this presupposes the reason why search
is valuable is because there's things to
search for but the second thing was
email which I'm sure some of us would
maybe quibble about and the third thing
though is digital Maps so people find
digital Maps like really invaluable to
their day-to-day existence now I think a
lot of us would probably kind of wonder
about like wow how did we even get
around before we could type in an
address and get directions to someplace
or even just find like a restaurant
nearby using Yelp or something like that
so digital maps at its heart kind of
have two basic parts and I know that
there are map nerds I'm sure on this and
they're going to quibble with what I say
and say like no you're being too simple
but well we'll get deeper as we go too
right so we can sort of start simple and
then dive deeper as we continue in at
its top level just to kind of get
orientation there's sort of two basic
parts here we have what's called a base
map and then your data that you want to
put on that base map so a base map is
largely kind of like the the roads and
the streets and the waterways the towns
in the world and that's something that
you don't probably as a developer it's
something that you don't want to have to
do like you don't want to have to have
to go and figure out like where all the
roads are at and stuff like that that
usually already comes available to you
through something called a base map but
also most of the time when you build a
digital map you're probably not wanting
just to show people where roads at you
want to show people where your data is
at in context to the base map so that's
the second part part of it is kind of
your data and often times that's kind of
the heart of the problem set getting
base Maps is fairly straightforward
there's a lot of different ways to get
base Maps now what are some of those
ways I mean I'm sure we're familiar with
Google Maps but what are some of the
others yeah I think Google Maps perfect
is a good example that almost
everybody's familiar with like when you
go to Google Maps and you look at the
world you're seeing what is kind of a
Google styled Bas map but Apple Maps has
their own base Maps there's you know
ezri which is one of the earliest
software inventors in the digital
mapping space it was started you know
back even back in the 70s actually they
were doing a you know initial
digitization of geospatial capacities
one kind of emerging and pretty really
interesting Bas map providers map box
but open street maps is an open source
and almost kind of a foundational
resource for digital mapping because it
empowers the world to kind of help map
the world and that's almost the only way
to do it you know there are some big
billion dooll companies like Google and
and apple that or navtech and stuff'll
drive around the world and with vehicles
and try to keep on top of it but when it
really boils down to it it really takes
a crowd to log and keep updated the data
of the world yeah and things are always
changing and I think that speaks to some
of the challenges that maybe you could
talk a little bit more about you
mentioned before we've got the Bas map
and then we've got the content and you
know in one way it just seems kind of
straightforward we'll just you know put
a pin on a map with a latitude longitude
and just start throwing content at it so
why is that
insufficient yeah I mean you know we
know the world is a lot more complicated
than just points on a map and oftentimes
as software
developers most of the time when we do
digital Maps it just the simplest and
the most straightforward way literally
is to put a pen on the map it's and a
pen is represented by a coordinate or
latitude longitude or a longitude
latitude that's an ongoing
debate But ultimately we know that the
world is more than that it's actually
paths so it's like routes like where
does this road go or where's this Trail
at or where is this you know where
that's a path or it could be an area so
an area is like a a Lake would be an
area or a property parcel would be an
area so at its heart those are
additional geometries of that represent
the kind of information that you want to
put on the earth and well it's a lot
simpler to just pass say like a you know
a latitude longitude coordinate as a
decimal value to something and it kind
of represents a point it gets a little
bit more complicated to say how do I
pass information that represents say an
area or a path and that's where a
standard is kind of evolved called that
most of the time now it's using
something called geojson which is a kind
of a subset of Json but it has a
geospatial capability so you can capture
geospatial information so you can then
pass a base map through a mapping
platform like either an API or SDK or
something and there's a lot of them out
there I
I'll mention some of them in a moment
here but you've got a base map now you
want to put your data on that map and
that data needs to be represented in a
in a structure that can capture not just
the simple points and paths but also
other geometries and best way to do that
is through geojson which is a
representation of that information so
let's pause on geojson I do want to dig
a little bit more into the details of
that later on in the episode but let's
stay a little bit high level for a
second and talk a little bit about how
we interact with the Bas map as software
Engineers because I imagine there's
different levels of detail for example
you mentioned you know yeah you can put
a point on a map but then you mention
paths and what's the distinction between
say when I'm responsible as a developer
to calculate such things or when I
should Leverage The mapping SDK or
mapping apis and what are some different
ways that I can make those decisions
about when it make sense for me to carry
a burden of calculation or determining
those things versus being able to rely
on the mapping platform itself to do
those sorts of things certainly most of
the time the mapping platform we can
talk about the platform here for a
moment we've got so let me amend the
idea of saying that there's just two
parts that you need and then add a third
part so you start with a base map and
then you've got your data but the way to
put your data on that map is typically
through a platform API or an SD K and
there are a lot of them out there you
know like let's go back to like the
Google Maps example with Google Maps you
could use the Google Maps API to pass it
data that you want to put on that base
map Apple map kit there's a lot of open-
source resources now one that's used a
lot is something called leaflet it's a
JavaScript mapbox has something called
mapbox GL but you know carto there's a
lot of sources out there and in fact
actually kind of it's going to depend on
the type of thing you're doing if you're
building an Apple iOS application you're
probably going to use apple mapkit SDK
you don't have to though you could use
mapbx or you could you could actually
even use like a Google Maps API to put
data into an Apple application so we've
got the base map we've got your data
then you want to put it into that now
your data is the platform itself self is
going to render that data but it's not
going to make that data for you with
some exceptions there are some things
that the platform sdks and apis will do
for you for example routing like if you
want to get directions from point A to
point B there are apis that you can kind
of pass the origin and the destination
information to and it'll render a route
for you and probably generate a uh
geojson representation of that route or
another type of representation of that
route now when you say route real quick
to clarify you know right now we're
talking about and I guess we talking
about driving what about things like you
know trail maps walking things that are
you know maybe you not going to send a
you know a car down a road to determine
these things in those kinds of use cases
you know is that a little more is on the
developer to figure out how to calculate
and determine those things yeah that's a
great question what we've done at this
point is we're really good at you know
the world is kind of evolved into a a
road metric Matrix with directions and
you can ask for driving directions but
if you ask for directions up the
Avalanche Trail in Glacier National Park
you're not going to get a result most
likely so once we get outside of the
road Matrix in some examples potentially
you know public transportation that's
sometimes getting a little better but
once you get outside of that if you want
to provide the data you're going to have
to do it or you're going to haveour
perhaps for you and crowdsourced yeah
that's a one way that kind of elevase
comes into play sometimes and something
like that or just a need to say like hey
I want to provide this data and I'm the
only one who has it or I can't go find
it out there sometimes this data exists
in the world World it may be proprietary
I find it a little bit too difficult to
you know like if you want to just put
say like a uh Summit County boundary on
a map finding a Summit County boundary
in a format that's usable and putting on
a map is harder than it should be but
that is starting to get easier okay and
what's making that challenging is it
about you know granularity and getting
the the details correct I mean maybe
talk a little bit about that because you
know it's it's fasc I think from a a b
you know a lot of people who aren't
familiar with technology generally it's
pretty amazing that you can do a Google
Earth and you can start way zoomed out
and you zoom way in I imagine there's
some challenges around just how accurate
things are based on how zoomed in or
zoomed out you are so how do you deal
with those kinds of challenges when
you're building mapping applications
finding the right resolution the right
level of scale and and being able to
answer you know these questions you know
we don't want to create a border dispute
between nations because we screwed up
our map right yeah speaking of Border
disputes actually just quick side
sideline on that we did a uh when I was
working with National Geographic on a
project and with USA ID also we built a
kind of collaborative travel guide to
the Western Balkans and it was really
cool because we had all these countries
that came together to represent you know
why people should visit the Balkans and
then like literally the day before we
launched the serbians decided that the
Border wasn't in the right
place of course there was a border
dispute so there you go that speaks to
the nature of the challenge right is is
these things are not static but they're
often Dynamic how was that challenge
addressed I mean was that an easy just
fix obviously the political side of it
probably wasn't as simple but I mean you
know what what's the response to that
kind of a you know situation yeah so the
good thing is that most of the time
those aren't problems that developers
need to worry about like the boundaries
on countries and such usually will come
from the base map and the base Maps
often times are deferring to have some
kind of standards and rules behind that
like for example I think in the instance
with Western Balkans guide you know we
were able to just lean back to National
Geographic who is kind of a partner in
state we're just following their
cardgraphic standards whether people
like it or not that's the standard that
we're following there are other so there
are groups they're kind of cardgraphic
groups that establish standards and kind
of rules for
whether something is a fixed boundary or
maybe you know and sometimes if enough
people don't agree on it they'll create
a dotted line and call it disputed or
something like that but that kind of
data most of the time will come from
base
Maps Okay so that means the developer
can rely on the base map typically to
take care of that sort of thing but I'm
kind of envisioning that it's not really
a hard line between what really would
belong in a base map and what might be
more you have to add yourself I mean is
that does that change over time do the
base Maps tend to take on you know more
granular data about you know location
and borders and things over time or is
there kind of a cutof point where it's
like okay they've done their job and now
it's time for you to do your your job
that is a great question and it kind of
leads into the way that mapping is
evolving and we're moving away from the
fixed boundaries between the base map
and your data that lays on top of the
Bas Bas map and things are moving more
towards these ideas of vector tiles and
Vector tile sets and there's a couple
reasons for that when you think about a
base map in the kind of the the more
Legacy Concepts is that you just got
that data you get it like you you know
Google Maps will give you the base map
but you can't decide like oh I don't
like what Google thinks is a boundary
and what isn't a boundary or there's
some capacity that they give you as a
developer to style those base Maps but
often times it's just kind of in colors
and Hues you don't have a lot of
granular control over that part of the
reason is because in a Legacy Way
creating a base map which if you think
about it is an enormous amount of data
and it kind of oftentimes it's
represented as almost like a triangle
where if you look at the entire world
the entire world could maybe be captured
through four different squares
but as you start to zoom in closer
you're exponentially needing more
squares until you get to the level of
like maybe streets and at that point
we're talking about millions and
millions of squares that are needed to
represent the entire
world rendering that data in the old
days took a lot of processing time and
it was usually get rendered in like a ra
with a raster file so a base map was
largely just kind of of an image of the
of that place kind of like a picture
it's just collect it's just assembling a
whole bunch of pictures that had been
pre-processed to make that and at
various layers of resolution I imagine
so you're saying when you're zoomed out
you've got picture you zoom in and then
how many Zoom levels do we have I
imagine was part of you know if you have
100,000 Zoom levels it's going to be way
more data than if you have
10,000 right yes definitely and so but
now we're moving to this other thing so
you said Vector tile sets so we've got
rasterizing so what is a vector tile set
in relation to to what we were doing
previously so there's no set numerical
value to it but in general when you're
interacting with base Maps there's kind
of levels and they'll call them Zoom
levels and zoom level one means sort of
the world and zoom level 22 could be
it's possible to even get below a zoom
level 22 but a zoom level 22 is like f
your looking at a street corner or
something is there a reason why 22 no
and there isn't really a fixed like like
if you go and you say like I want to
look at a zoom level eight on ezri and a
zoom level eight on Google Map Bas map
or a zoom level eight on a map box
they're not going to be exactly the same
like they won't align exactly the same
you can't but somewhere 20ish seems to
be kind of common we we don't have a 100
or a thousand Zoom levels but we also
don't just have 10
yeah I mean I think if you got to a 100
zoom level you sort of run out of you
know you're getting down to the
centimeter and super granular yeah yeah
you just run out of stuff to show that
people care the utility would have
decreased I imagine at that level like
it's just too much granularity too much
data exactly yeah okay at about 22 is
about where you get in close enough that
so going back to the early days when we
did our initial kind of Coleman outernet
map it was just
it was almost magic when the very first
time we took all this data we've been
developing and kind of crowd sourcing
and and put it on a map and suddenly all
these places of these icons showed up on
a on a digital map and it's like sudden
you know all this data that had been
kind of tabular was now in front of us
in a visual way or a spatial way but it
was on a base map that wasn't that
interesting it was largely just kind of
like beige the roads were there but
anything that wasn't a road was kind of
beige and the reason for that is because
the amount of computing power would take
to render all the details just didn't
exist at that time but now when you go
off of a road it's not just a beige area
you've got the topography and you've got
all kinds of interesting stuff that used
to be kind of rendered through a visual
but now you can render that as a vector
data and a vector data meaning that it's
actually just described through geometry
the computer understands the geometry of
it instead of just rendering raster
squares the really interesting thing is
that one as we all probably know a bit
is that loading Vector information is a
lot faster than loading you know kind of
raster images this would be like
scalable vector graphics versus you know
jpegs right like a JPEG is a raster
representation of an image with some Com
or PNG and then you got an SVG and that
also shifts the rendering burden as well
right yes who renders this yep and most
of the time it's kind of rendered
through the browser or through the
device you mean now with the the vector
tile sets correct yes okay y so that
moves some of the processing burden to
the edge or not even the edge to the
client but then since it's vector-based
I imagine that reduces that burden on
the rendering so it distributes it and
then it's also simplifying it because
it's Vector based yes Y and the other
thing happens it's still a tile set
though and that's what it's still tiles
so they use this IDE of tile which is
squares so if you say you want to have a
map of the world you don't download the
entire world into your browser because
that would be too much but at the same
time is you never look at the detail
like you don't look at the street level
detail of the entire world at the same
time in fact you probably will never
look at the street level detail of the
whole world so it's only going to bring
in the tile data that's necessary for
this for the window that you're looking
at you say window do you mean level or
does that is that different than when
you say window window and level are kind
of the same thing but they're slightly
different in the sense that like if you
have a big screen you might be including
more tiles than I see I see so the
window is the and it's hard CU we're on
a podcast here so you can't see our
hands moving here but essentially the
window is like a window it's the
rectangle I'm looking at right now and
then the level is how far zoomed in I am
at the given time that's correct yeah
yeah they're going to be you know if if
you're really zoomed in it's going to
take a really huge window to have a you
know to show a lot of
neighborhoods now if you're really
zoomed out you can kind of capture the
entire world in just your viewport so to
speak right but that may be of limited
utility depending on what you're trying
to do yeah so what's changing now for
developers with the shift from more
raster based you know you talked about
the early days you know when you first
built you know applications in the 90s
doing this and you know was obviously
raster based and it was rendering on you
know some either pre-rendering I would
imagine or being rendered at request
time by some you know heavy server in
the back end how are tile sets affecting
the ways that developers interact with
maps now yeah so I think a couple ways
you know out of the gate I said that
there's kind of two basic things you've
got the base map and then you've got
your data and you put your data on top
of the base map most of the time people
probably look at interactive maps and
they see like that and then they one
experience they often have will be a
just a kind of a cluster or a grouping
of icons that are all just crowding out
the information underneath it and that's
because what you're seeing is your data
being represented by icons on a base map
and as you zoom zoom out further it just
you know there's just not enough space
to show those with Vector tile sets your
data and the base Maps start to
intermingle a bit and you start thinking
of a vector tile set as a series of
layers and you might have for example a
a layer that is just water ways that's
represented as a vector tile set and in
that Vector tile set has characteristics
and Associated data with it and a lot of
it is styling characteristics like we
want the water to be blue and we want
the water to appear when you're between
this zoom level and that that zoom level
okay interesting yeah just because when
you're very far zoomed out and you're
trying to see the whole world you can't
show every little river and stuff it
just makes the map it just wouldn't work
so you're saying like hey at this zoom
level another way to think about that
sometimes when you think about like Town
labels or Street labels like the street
that I live on is not going to be
visible on the map when I'm showing the
entire country partly because if I
showed every street at that level the
map would be a mess however I with the
tile set I would have the control to
show just my street level at that if I
wanted I could pick out that little
piece of data let me use another example
of how vector sets are a little bit more
valuable in the sense is that because
it's Vector data and it has the styling
attributes kind of embedded with the
data you can start to change the
presentation or change the design or the
visual representation on the fly so just
like you could with you know other
vector graphics through a browser or
through a device so an example of that
would be if I want to have boundaries so
each country boundary is represented as
a vector you know as Vector tile data
and then if I wanted to say like
population and population as a value is
actually embedded as part of that tile
set it's metadata for that tile set so
in my code I could say if the population
value is higher than 1 billion make it
red if it's between 1 billion and 200
million make it orange if it's less than
200 million make it yellow or something
like that can you also use that
information to control at what level of
Zoom cities will appear or not appear
for example because I imagine that's
useful for your Maps right if I'm zoomed
out look at the US I might want to see
New York Los Angeles you know Portland
Oregon of course because that's where I
live you know Denver because right you
know what I mean anyway so I imagine
that's part of the control set too is
you can I do that when I'm interacting
with these mapping sdks as a developer
yeah one of the attributes in a vector
tile is the visibility layer is the
visibility value and you can decide at
what value that is present or not
present now a lot of this to people
might sound like oh my gosh that's a lot
how do I do all of this there are tools
that like you don't necessarily have to
write the vector tile data yourself you
like you don't have to like write the T
the and even write the design
specifications there are tools out there
like for example mapbox has a really
nice kind of visual editor where you can
go into mapbox and design you know you
can pick all of that and make the map
look exactly the way you want it to look
there's map Tyler there are open-source
tools out there there's one called map I
probably mispronounced the name map
mapup Nick map EU or m
u tiik mapup Nick which is an open
source kind of
tile set designer through a UI the cool
thing with maps now is that in the old
days you got what you got now you make
the map what you want it to be and you
can decide like hey you know what my map
I don't really want the town names it's
not important to what I'm doing with my
interactive map putting the town names
on there that's just clutter or it might
be a map that's really specific about
say hydrology or something like that you
say I don't even want the streets on
there I just want to focus on say like
the the topography and the waterways
that's the kind of data I want to put on
my map and you can do that now with map
tiles you can style the map so it's the
map that you want and then your data
itself can also be rendered as tile sets
and it exists within that layer system
however you want so essentially you can
take the tile sets that they're
providing create your own and then
determine how those sort of combine
together to create your map yes so going
back to the idea of tile set you
probably don't want to build like I
don't even know probably don't want to I
probably you're not capable or don't
have the space to do that to build a
tile set of like all the waterways in
the world or all the roads and stuff so
those tile sets exist out there one
place that's actually a really good
resource from that is something like
open street
maps however most mapping platforms that
you interact with whether it's Google
Maps or ezri or mapbox map Tyler most of
the time when you're using their
platform they'll give you the base Maps
they'll give you a certain amount of
data out of the box which is kind of
representing the world so let's talk
about a real world scenario you know I
think most of us are familiar with
navigation apps I think a lot of us have
forgotten how to get anywhere just like
we can't remember anybody's phone number
anymore or their email address so we're
so used to Maps so
what's happening when I'm like imagine
it's using location information from my
phone like talk us through because you
know let's say our listeners may want to
do some mapping apps of themselves so
understand a little bit about what's
going on right now to help render that
map on my iPhone or my Android phone or
whatever how's that interacting with the
mapping base and this is a simple use
case we can get into some more complex
ones in a second in order to you know
render things like real-time traffic and
my real time location as it pertains to
where I am in the map and where I am in
reality yeah so there's a really
interesting Confluence that kind of
happened with the Advent of the
smartphone where suddenly people were
carrying around their computers or
carrying around their devices on so your
location became really really relevant
to the whole kind of question of what
you could do early days with online
mapping and such you would go to a
desktop computer and you would say what
address are you going to start and you
would type that in and then you'd say
where do you want to end and you type
that in it would give you directions and
you'd print them out carry them in car
with you either that or earli you had a
Thomas guide but yes that the early
stage of the internet I remember having
my printed directions with me in my car
yep yeah I one of the kind of going back
to the days I was working on a licensing
deal with Map Quest and their
headquarters were in Washington DC so I
flew into Washington DC and I before I
went I printed out my directions and I
followed them you know in my rental car
how to get I'd get there and they're
like how did they work and I said no
they're pretty good you know you got
there so I mean yeah yeah most of the
time it work so you know a couple things
are happening now with everybody having
the device your computer's on your
device so it knows where you're at
sometimes even if you didn't give a
permission to know that but that's
another thing so it knows where you're
at and because of that location based
information or contextual information
becomes you know there's all kinds of
use cases that have emerged out of that
driving directions being just one but
think about how often we can start
answering questions that we have in our
head that our location is relevant to
such as what's a good restaurant where I
can get some sushi when I don't want to
go more than five minutes in a car or I
don't want to walk more than five
minutes you know where can I charge my
electric car all these kind of spatial
questions that really are key to our
everyday life you know we exist in a
world in a physical world with the
physical infrastructure and most of the
questions or a lot of the questions we
have and the problems we have every day
is in relationship to that physical
question that physical infrastructure
that's probably one of the reasons why
you know that study by MIT found that
digital maps are you know the third most
valuable thing that people found yeah
and then you know you said was it search
email and then digital Maps but I'm
curious how much search actually is
related to location in other words like
you said find me a restaurant is that a
search or is that a digital map and I
think it's you could kind of doesn't
necess mutually exclusive I think is
what I'm I think they blend together
very much you know most of the time when
you do a Google Search now even on your
desktop it's going to prioritize that
information based on where you're at
yeah and I think we take it so for
granted now which makes me curious to
you know before we dig a little more
into some of the nuts and bolts of
geojson which I definitely want to do
before we run out of time but what are
some use cases that you see developing
now with some of these changes with
Vector tile sets you know what's sort of
the state of where we're going with maps
so that maybe you know some of our
listeners have ideas about oh because in
some ways you might say it's
overwhelming there's so much we're doing
now with maps that maybe there's nothing
left to be done and I imagine the
opposite is the case there's probably a
ton left to do do and I'm curious what
your thoughts are on where are we going
next what could we do to continue
pushing this yeah I think that we're
kind of at the start of it in a lot of
ways I think that going back to the idea
that you know many of the questions and
many of the pieces of information that
we want are related to where we exist
you know or they have a geographical
context and I think that as software
developers I think software development
is just kind of at the early Edge of
starting to take into account spatial
questions there's unfortunately or for
whatever reason there's been a little
bit of a a division there's kind of GIS
people who are trained to be kind of GIS
stands for geographic information
systems or sort of cartography
professionals that were the map makers
and they lived over in this one camp and
then over in this other Camp there were
software developers who wrote code and
there wasn't a lot of intersection in
that but now there's been a merging of
that where now regular software
developers can start to interact and
start using geospatial Tools in ways
that before were maybe only available to
the gis professional and so what are
some of the questions that you might
want to ask and this is where I would
start is start asking like how can I
know like what information is inside of
a specific polygon sometimes people use
the term Geo fencing for that which is
I've got a polygon and it's not just a
circle it's actually a more nuanced and
complicated it's like maybe a block and
I want to know what information is
inside of that there's a lot of ways to
organize data and to sort in the query
data based on a simple thing like that
or another one could be I want to know
like what information is along a path
you know along a route knowing things
about like elevation and those are
things that add a lot of value to end
users that if you put them into the
context of what the features are in your
software right I could go one other way
with it too I think that one thing
that's happening also in the mapping
space is we're starting to get better at
some of the last mile you know and
trying to is people are starting to
expect more information on that last
mile so over time we've refined and
we've built a pretty good data set that
understands where the roads are at in
the world and how to drive from point A
to point B but once you get out of your
car like you know I think the next I
guess Frontier in the space of kind of
more like indoor mapping people will say
like how do I get from this place to
this room within a hospital complex or
within a university or things like that
yeah that could be really helpful you
show up at a building and you don't know
which floor and it could be a big floor
and that can get really really granular
but could be really powerful as well
yeah I think we navigate around
structures a little bit the way we did
in say 1985 still asking people yeah
that's an interesting Insight right the
technology has really worked for the
broad scale but that last you called it
the last mile but it's like the last
yard it's like get me here and I you
know I see attempts to try to do that
sometimes when I park my mapping app
will say would you like to walk the last
you know bit and it'll actually help me
do that but seems like there's some
opportunity to lean into that as well
and then I guess too you know we've
hinted a little bit at there's obviously
consumer applications for mapping but
then there's also a lot of you know
industrial commercial applications for
this as well so are there I mean you
know I think some of us have probably
experienced where getting a package
delivered and sometimes at least in my
experience not always and I don't
remember which vendor or which provider
does this but I've had times where it
will send me an interactive map of where
the truck is right now now that I'm
supposed to be working so if sitting
there watching my package you know it's
limited utility on the other hand it's
kind of cool if you're like because who
doesn't love getting a package right but
you know talk a little bit about the you
know because some of this too John and I
know you've seen this too in your
experiences some of the things we've
seen for location you know I remember
there were apps where you could like
check in everywhere and was like
checking checking checking and this was
cute for about a week and then you
realize why am I checking in everywhere
that I go I'm not really getting much
out of this so there's some limited
utility use cases and then there's some
higher utility use cases so can you
speak a little a little bit about how
you've seen that play out in your years
in mapping what's sort of proven to not
be super valuable use cases and which
things are going to be growth use cases
maybe going forward yeah and I think
that there's actually some science
behind it where let's say for example a
public transit system and you're waiting
at a bus stop or you're waiting for a
train to
arrive and the science behind it is that
if they show you where the current bus
is at in relationship to your place or
how long it's going to be if they tell
you that or show you that the perceived
amount of time that you have to wait is
significantly Less in fact even like
half the amount so if you're standing at
a bus stop and it's kind of chilly and
you got five minutes to wait for a bus
and you don't know like is the bus going
to show up is it on its way is it even
anywhere do they even know I'm here if
those are all the questions that are
running through your head that five
minutes seems like 20 minutes but if you
can see it on the map and you can see
that that bus is on its way that five
minute starts to feel like two minutes
so there is some science behind that
whether or not it's like you know
certainly this is probably a first world
problem like you know my emotional state
of having to worry about that bus is
maybe not solving a super critical
problem but it does improve just a
person's experience with something that
public transit system or even the
transit system itself that's probably
one of the reason right really early on
Uber started to show where that car is
at yeah freeways have for a long time
been saying this many minutes from here
to here based on traffic and there's
obviously you know you're not using a
mapping app on your phone but there's
you know geospatial implications for
that and I imagine reducing road rage is
good for Humanity even if it you know
tends to be yeah not maybe the biggest
problem we have to solve yeah or another
thing that it can be solving is helping
disperse traffic it's like ah I don't
want to wait 50 minutes one problem that
National Parks have right now is that
something like 93% of visitors visit or
what I think it's actually 97% of
visitors visit 3% of the
park and so you have these really
popular places like yede in the valley
bottom of you know the valley floor or
the rim of the Grand Canyon or you know
these places where everybody goes and
there's times where there will be
potentially a 5H hour wait
for someone just in car sitting there in
the car to get into the the valley
bottom of yede so how do you solve that
problem well number one is know that it
exists and two could be potentially
telling people like hey it's five hours
but if you go here or go there you could
also have an interesting experience yeah
and that sounds similar in some ways to
getting different routing directions
based on traffic profiles but this is
it's the same thing but it's not
car-based it's it's a traffic profile of
standing in line you know yeah that's
interesting you know I haven't been to
an amusement park in a while either but
I would be shocked if they don't have
apps that tell you this as well how long
do I have to wait in line for you know
Space Mountain and and these kinds of
things so now the information itself is
potentially valuable because I can make
a decision but if it told me something
else to do also that I could as an
alternative that would that even adds to
the value so I think that you know when
we think about like how to use
geospatial information in our feature
development it's not really just about
the technical capacity but what is the
problem that it's solving for humans and
that's where it really starts becoming
useful because like if I've got an app
and it's going to show me where taco
restaurants are and it says hey John
there's this really great taco
restaurant but it's like three hours
away or it's on the other side of a
mountain or it's like a long way you
know it's not accessible to me those
better be some great tacos
yeah yeah the app isn't that helpful to
me so it's you know or if it's like hey
John there's five hours if you want to
you know you can sit in your car for the
next five hours or you could go and do
these other things in these other
communities that starts becoming
interesting to me because it's like oh
wow thank you for saving me from sitting
in my car for five hours but what else
has it's done it's taken like all this
spending power that's sitting in a car
and distributing it out into these rural
communities that have you know great
little restaurants that would love to
have more customers so we can help solve
those very real problems by thinking
about not just the capacity the
technical capability of doing that but
actually what are the real world human
problems that we're solving so let's
talk a little bit it's you know again
challenging with audio only but you've
mentioned before sdks and apis for some
of these mapping platforms and we'll put
links in the show notes to a lot of
these you know different things if
listeners want to dive in a little bit
more deeply but you mentioned geojson
before so let's say I have an idea for
adding interactive maps to an
application that I'm working on or a new
product that I want to build or these
kinds of things so talk a little bit
about helping a listener get started
what does geojson look like what are
they embedding in there are there tools
that help am I just in vs code coding
this up by scratch you know how am I
getting started here as somebody who
wants to get into involved with mapping
Technologies so often times and this is
probably one of the reasons why little
pin drops on a map are the most common
ways that most software developers kind
of think about an interactive map I was
like oh I want to put a pen on the map
and it's got a little pop over and stuff
and the reason why is because that's
it's a pretty easy way to represent
geospatial data you can do it with a lot
of mapping applications just by passing
a CSV file so if okay oh so you could
start there so it sounds like pin drops
sort of mapping apps what chat Bots are
to AI right now in a little ways it's
like or maybe it's like putting a photo
into a web pages you know it's like sort
of the basics you can do it you know it
accomplishes something you know it's
nice to know that this place is where
it's at that has value to people you
could get driving directions there or
something so at it's very foundational
level you can use a CSV with a lot of
things and that CSV obviously would need
to have two columns a latitude and a
longitude or a longitude and a Latitude
it depends on once again sometimes I can
be fighting words over the order of that
and then you can have your other
information like it could be description
and it could be another thing like a
status or type so you can you can
represent geospatial information as a
CSV you can pass that CSV to a mapping
application and quite often the mapping
application you know the platform API
whether it's like a Google Maps or ezri
or something like that they recognize it
they can see oh I understand those are
coordinates so quickly make a static map
with points using a flat file and that's
going to take you only so far right so
now we've got the issue of it's static
it's not Dynamic and then we've got the
issue that it's flat and not structured
so what can I do let's maybe go down the
structured we can talk about the dynamic
versus static in a second but so now I
move from flat file to geojson what
changes what can I now do differently
that I couldn't do before with the flat
file so geojson you can start to
represent that information as paths and
polygons and not only that but think
about it going Beyond just a path like a
path isn't always just a path you could
have a path that's a dirt Trail or you
could have a path that's a paved trail
or you have a path that's say like
universally accessible so if you wanted
to have a path and you want to show that
hey this path isn't just a path it
actually has different types of paths
you know like the pave path you want
want to have is a thicker line that's
gray and a dirt path might want is a
dotted line or something like that
that's brown so those types of paths and
the data associated with it could all be
represented as geojson and it's just a
Json representation it's a Json
structure the reason why they call it
geojson is because there's a
specification that understands how to
capture and structure that geospatial
information now we're getting into a
space where it's like you know I could
see a developer going like how do I make
a geojson file if I don't have my own
geojson file you know or if I don't like
import it from someone else you can use
tools out there like
arcgis there are you know some platforms
that have rgis online which is a ezri
tool there are different kind of ways to
sort of do that through browsers and
such now one of the limitations of it is
is that you're really just now dealing
with the Geo dat so like okay now I've
drawn a line I've drawn an area I have a
go Json file but you probably want to do
more than that you want to actually
describe it have descriptions and maybe
you want to have photos of that trail
and stuff like that and that's kind of
one of the ways that elevase comes into
play is it's sort of designed for
building Advanced Geo data sets like
this that go far beyond just you know
kind of like the point and path
information where you want a lot of your
media also your long descriptions or
lots of photos and maybe video or
attributes and stuff like that so there
are tools like that then you would
access that data through the API and the
data would be presented to you as a gojs
on that you could just put on the map
okay now let's say I need to more
interactively update my map like
dynamically in real time right now what
I have in mind which I'm guessing is not
correct is I'm not just throwing in a
CSV file at the map every like 250
milliseconds so so if I can alter a map
or add features to a map using geojson
that's one thing but now if I need this
interactivity and this Dynamic updates
how is that working are these simple API
calls is there more to it you know
what's going on there yeah I mean you
can the geojson file or the CSV file is
kind of you know a one hit thing or
you're going to add it and then it's
going to be there now if you want to
dynamically interact act you can
dynamically access uh Json or geojson
through an API and so that's you know
once again I don't want to like just fog
elevas on this but that's kind of like
one of the things that you can get out
of elevase is just like get this data
through an endpoint yeah well actually
no that's great timing so let's
transition to talk a little bit about
elase with the time that we have left so
you have a company called elase we
mentioned at the top of the show we've
talked about mapping applications
broadly you know kind of how they work
how developers can get started with
working with them so so what does a tool
like elase help developers do that they
would be challenged to you know do for
themselves with interactive mapping and
geospatial applications so going back to
the kind of the foundational point which
is that you most of the time when you
build a digital map you want to put your
data on that map like the base map
itself has contextual value but in
itself it's you know just stuff that you
can pretty much get anywhere so when you
make your own digital map the primary
value proposition of that digital map is
that you're showing your information and
that information consists of kind of two
parts for the most part it's the
geographical information like where are
the points at where's the polygons what
kind of polygons what kind of points are
those but then there's another step to
it which is often times the details
behind that so just to to use kind of
something we probably all relate to
maybe is Trail information so if you
want to have an interactive map like for
example the monana Wilderness
Association has this really cool
interactive map called hike Wild Montana
with hundreds of trails all across
Montana that have been crowd sourced and
that's they're using elase to power that
and what happens is you look at the map
and there's a point and then as you zoom
in there's actually the route of the
trail and then you can SCT it and you
can learn about that trail like you can
see photos of that trail you can see
descriptions you can see characteristics
like is it good for kids you know all of
that
information typically has to be when
people are building an interactive map
what they're doing is they're often
times marrying or relating the Geo
information with another database
they're saying like Okay we're going to
go manage all the trail information here
in this resource and then we're going to
like create an ID or something and link
to the other information over here so
they either have to build it custom or
they have to kind of connect that with
Elbas that's kind of all just in the
same platform and it's done in a way
that's kind of designed for the regular
developer not for GIS professionals it's
not like you've you you don't have to go
get a degree in GIS to access this
information as you would pretty much any
API okay yeah because what you're
describing I mean I remember a while
back doing some mapping applications
with some GIS extensions to postgressql
and you were able to use that to do even
proximity search and things of that
nature to find coordinates that were
close to one another and things of that
nature or if they fit within a certain
zip code that was another thing that we
could we could do with that but of
course that required you to know
postgressql required you to kind of
understand how the gis extensions worked
and this sort of a thing and so it
sounds like a platform like elase might
simplify the accessibility to those
kinds of features and functionality for
people who want to get started doing
mapping applications yeah it kind of
abstracts that so you could pass it a
polygon and it's going to give you that
information as a parameter in the
endpoint you know so you don't have to
stand up postcript SQL and run it and
all of that and maintain it and scale it
it's kind of there the Wild Montana is
kind of an interesting example of that
because they have so in that hike or in
that guide they have all these what they
call kind of local businesses that they
want to help support
and those businesses are near Trail
heads so if you're looking at a trail it
would say like oh here's a nearby
business too that you want to see the
the problem set that they had though is
that okay how do I show local
businesses in one way that people
oftentimes without you know manually
going and relating all these things and
keeping all these relationships in place
so you just want to do a spatial query
like here's the trail head show me
everything nearby it and that's what
oftentimes people will do is they'll
just do do like the radius search show
me everything within 30 air miles of
that in Montana what happened is you'd
often times get like a restaurant that's
on the other side of the mountain in a
valley so by the crow flies it's 30
miles but driving it's 200 so you needed
a more interesting query which is like
okay you needed a contains within so
with elevase what they could do is draw
a little polygon around that say like
hey any business that's inside of this
area is is a related business and then
dynamically that would just show up on
the page like they didn't have to you
know when they loaded that it just show
me all the businesses that are inside
this polygon yeah so it's helped me with
managing the content itself but also the
placement of that content within the map
and it's kind of lowering that barrier
to entry and on top of it it then allows
like you know going back to the initial
idea that most of the time it's lot
better to have a thousand people
maintaining one piece of information
each than to have one person maintaining
a thousand pieces of information a map
of the world is really difficult for
just a few people to do so Elbas kind of
empowers large communities of people to
collaborate on that information you know
through a user interface that's kind of
designed for non-experts an example of
that like the state of Maine uses elase
the power the visit main.com and to have
non-experts you need to have say like a
local restaurant owner in Caribou Maine
that's able to log in and update
information without going through a Long
training course right yeah and there's
times where that makes sense you know
it's like I appreciate the experience
I've had diving deep into you know ezri
and rgis and postgressql you know GIS
capabilities and things like that but
that required a lot of effort and work
to understand the nuts and bolts of that
and also I was doing this 15 years ago
when you know tools like what you're
describing didn't exist but sometimes as
a software engineer you want to find the
shortest path to releasing the
functionality and getting the product
out of the marketplace and so having
tools like that that can help lower that
barrier to entry not just for developers
but also for other people that are using
the applications sounds really great
well John anything else you want to
share with our listeners before we wrap
things up anything else they should know
or research or about what you're up to
these days oh yeah wow I mean God it's
such a big space you know mapping and
GIS is you know a whole H in itself but
I think probably just in kind of quick
summary is like it is a discipline that
is intersecting a lot more with just
regular software development and so
start thinking about ways you know as
you're building new software adding new
features and such just what are the
spatial components what are the spatial
questions that you could potentially
solve for and some of that has to do
with just the primary vectors of you
know what's nearby
where is the location in context to
other things just those kind of use
cases that impact us in a real world
level and know kind of as a as a human
level the tools for accomplishing that
are becoming much more I guess
accessible and usable for developers in
their code and so if we're not thinking
about that I think there's a possibility
that other people are as you kind of
wake up one morning you'll figure out
that you know you might learn that wow
my application isn't Geo aware or it's
not thinking about geography or
geospatial questions at all and these
other people are and that's maybe why
they're getting you know more uptake
yeah I think that's great to consider
and as you said you know from that
research that the top three uses of the
internet search email and digital maps
and they' become so ubiquitous now that
sometimes when things become ubiquitous
we stop seeing them but you know you're
encouraging us to realize that there
could be opportunities we'd be missing
out on if we don't consider how to
include geospace and mapping
Technologies in our Solutions so that's
great John if people want to find out
more about you and about elase where
should they go yeah you can go to
lease. and at elias. there's actually a
free trial you can take with elase it's
free to try it out you don't have to
give a credit card or anything like that
and the API is right there and pretty
well
documented you know try it out have fun
well John thanks so much for joining me
on software engineering radio thanks
Jeff all right this is Jeff D for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]